Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Foxhall Road Campus Collection, 1946-1999 MVC0006.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Foxhall Road Campus Collection
1930-2000
1946-1980
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary
Mount Vernon College
MVC0006.RG
6.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains photographs, negatives, contact sheets, as well as various press releases, minutes, and correspondence documenting the campus, students, and staff of Mount Vernon Seminary and College during the period from 1946 to 1999 when it was located on Foxhall Road.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: images and documents.
Biographical / Historical
Mount Vernon Seminary and Junior College moved from its Nebraska Avenue location in 1942 to make way for the United States Navy, and remained in temporary quarters in the Spring Valley neighborhood until 1946, when it reopened at 2100 Foxhall Road. This collection documents the Foxhall Road campus with photos of students, campus events, and buildings from 1946 to 1999, when the college and its campus became part of The George Washington University. It also includes some documents such as minutes, correspondence, and clippings that date as early as 1940.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains photographs, negatives, contact sheets, as well as various press releases, minutes, and correspondence documenting the campus, students, and staff of Mount Vernon Seminary and College during the period from 1946 to 1999 when it was located on Foxhall Road. Images include publicity photos, formal photos of students, snapshots by students and staff, and photos of commencement, student activities, and alumnae activities. Documents, some of which date to 1940, include faculty meeting minutes, some administrative correspondence, pamphlets, programs, press releases, and promotional materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Other Finding Aids
There are many collections from the Mount Vernon Archives that contains similar topics and types of content to that found within this collection. Please use http://library.gwu.edu/scrc/search/finding-aids-by-topic/mount-vernon-seminary-and-college for a complete list.
- Images, 1930-1998; 1946-1980; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Several boxes were added at later dates, so the contents of those boxes were separately arranged in chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photographs, negatives, and contacts sheets documenting the campus, students, and staff of Mount Vernon Seminary and College during the period from 1946 to 1999 when it was located on Foxhall Road. They include publicity photos, formal photos of students, snapshots by students and staff, and photos of commencement, student activities, and alumnae activities.
  - Photocopies of photos, including graduation and wartime, c. 1930-1970; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Academic studies, 1946-69; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Interiors, 1946-69; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photos of theater productions, music, dance, and athletics, c. 1946-69; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Special events, 1946-69; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Student life [1 of 5], 1946-69; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Student life [2 of 5], 1946-69; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Student life [3 of 5], 1946-69; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Student life [4 of 5], 1946-69; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Student life [5 of 5], 1946-69; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Posters, campus plans, 1946-74; Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Campus photos, 1949; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Horse show, 1949; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Senior Class Night, 1949; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Student activites -- drama and dance, 1949-63; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Alumnae activities on campus, c. 1950; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Benefits - book fairs, c. 1950; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Benefits - fashion show, c. 1950; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Student actitivies -- Chapel Guild, c. 1950; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Classroom scenes, contact sheets and photographs, c. 1950-1960; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Commencement photos, contact sheets, c. 1950-60; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Student and campus scenes, c. 1950-60; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Student and campus scenes, c. 1950-60; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Alumnae Councils, c. 1950-70; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Folk singers -- college and prep, c. 1950-70; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Publicity photos, c. 1950-70; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Campus, students, alumnae, and guest speakers, 1950-95; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Founders Day, 1955; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Fathers' Day, College, c. 1955-60; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Student and campus scenes, contact sheets, c. 1955-65; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Student and campus scenes, negatives, c. 1955-65; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Student and campus scenes, negatives and contact sheets, c. 1955-65; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Students and staff posed on campus, negatives, c. 1955-65; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Campus, students, and alumnae, 1955-80; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Student activities -- choir and glee club, 1956; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - May festival, 1956-61; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Student activities -- formal dances and inauguration, 1956-62; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Reunion weekends, 1956-65; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Exteriors, negatives, 1957; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Student body leaders, 1957-62; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Founders' Day at Hillwood, 1959; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photos and memorabilia from Ann Goldsmith Hanaw (S'59), Dear Daughters page 167, c. 1959; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Student trips, Williamsburg, 1959; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Students, informal, 1959-63; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae activities away from campus, c. 1960; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Christmas activities, c. 1960; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Forum, c. 1960; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Student activities -- children's work for c.d.m. majors, c. 1960; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Student scenes, contact sheets, c. 1960; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Student photos, head and shoulder shots, c. 1960-69; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Faculty photos [1 of 2], Circa 1960s-1970s; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Faculty photos [2 of 2], Circa 1960s-1970s; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Campus and student scenes, contacts and negatives, 1962; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Summer programs -- Red Cross seminar, 1962; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Alumnae Bulletin group photo, Spring 1962; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Peter Pelham, 5th president of Mount Vernon, 1962-76; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Student scenes, contact sheets, c. 1963; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Student scenes, contact sheets, 1963; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Contact sheets, 1964; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Student activities -- opening of school, 1964; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fathers' Day, prep school, 1965; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Washington Summer Program, 1965; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Campus scenes, negatives (by Tedd Kelly, Director of Development), 1965-66; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of T. Mills Kelly, January 2011, Acc. 2011.004
  - Photos of students, 1965-68; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Campus scenes, contact prints, c. 1965-80; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Campus scenes, contact prints, c. 1965-80; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Campus scenes, contact prints and negatives, c. 1965-80; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Campus scenes, contact prints and negatives, c. 1965-80; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Campus scenes, negatives, c. 1965-80; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Alumnae activities, 1966; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - College activites, 1966; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Founders Day, 1966; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Washington Summer Program, 1966; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - MVC Reunion (1967), Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Gymnastics show, 1968; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - MVC Reunion (1968), Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Patrick Hayes, speaker at D.C. Club Luncheon, 1968 March; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - MVC Reunion (1969), Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Founders Day, 1969 November 5; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Snowball battle (negatives), 1969 Winter; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Campus photos, Circa early 1970s; Series 1 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Commencement, 1970; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Founders Day, 1970; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Yearbook photos (negatives), 1970; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - MVC Reunion (1972), Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - MVC Reunion (1973), Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Commencement, 1974; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - MVC candid photos (contact sheets), 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Swimming pool construction, 1975; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Faculty and staff, photos, contact sheets, and negatives, c. 1975-85; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Faculty photos, G-L, c. 1980; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Baby photos, family and student scenes, 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Campus and student scenes, 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Campus and student scenes, 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Campus and student scenes, 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Campus and student scenes, 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Campus and student scenes, 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Campus and student scenes, 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Campus and student scenes, 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Faculty and staff, photos, c. 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Faculty and staff, photos, c. 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Faculty and staff, photos, c. 1980-90; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Students and campus scenes, 1980-96; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Student and campus scenes, contact sheets, c. 1980-96; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Students and campus scenes, negatives, c. 1980-96; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Students and campus scenes, photographs, c. 1980-96; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Students and campus scenes, slides, 1980-96; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Commencement, Circa 1980s; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Student candid photos, c. 1985-98; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Construction of library, photos, 1986; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Mount Vernon campus, 1987; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Alumnae in Austin, Texas, 1988 May 1; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Commencement, 1990; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Commencement, 1990 May; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Performing arts, c. 1990; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Graduation weekend, 1992 May 9-10; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Reunion, 1992; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 50th class reunion at Hillwood, undated; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Benefit fashion show, undated; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Campus exterior photos, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Celebrities on campus, undated; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Commencement, undated; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Faculty, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Last graduation photos, undated; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Mount Vernon Tennis Classic, undated; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Retirement Westfall Massev. Pollard (contact sheets), undated; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Special events, undated; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Staff and faculty, undated; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Students on campus, undated; Series 1 (Box 14, Folder 19)
- Documents, 1940-2000; 1950-1976; Series 2
  This series contains documents detailing the history of Mount Vernon Seminary and College from 1946 through 1999 during the years when the college was located on Foxhall Road. It contains faculty meeting minutes (some of which date to 1940), some administrative correspondence, pamphlets, programs, and promotional materials.
  - Minutes of faculty meetings, 1940-41; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Event programs, 1941-96; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of faculty meetings, 1942-43; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of faculty meetings, 1943-44; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Minutes of faculty meetings, 1944-45; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Press coverage, 1945-1967; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Diamond Jubliee program materials, 1950; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Mount Vernon College promotional booklets, 1950-96; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of faculty meetings, 1951-52; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Mount Vernon correspondence, timelines, and histories, 1951-98; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Minutes of faculty meetings, 1952-53; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Minutes of faculty meetings, 1953-54; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Press releases - publicity, 1955-1957; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Opening of Post Hall, 1956-1957; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Press releases, 1956-1962; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Program for joint concert with Valley Forge Military Academy, 1959 February 28; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Mount Vernon Junior College Committee on Student Activites, 1960-1962; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1961-91; series 2 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Columbia Scholastic Press Association First Place Certificate for the Cupola, 1963 October 11; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Press coverage, 1963-1964; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Department of Health, Education, and Welfare regarding Enrollment and Physical Facilities Survey, 1966; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Master Site Plan correspondence, 1966; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Special events committee, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Annual Antique Show, 1970-72; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - D.C. Alumnae Club's Antique Show, 1971 October-1972 February; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Remarks and Addresses Presented on the Occasions of the 1972 Academic Convocation and 98th Founder's Day, Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Annual Antique Show correspondence, 1972-83; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "The Spirit of '76" - 1973 Inaugural Guide, Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Event Advertisements, 1974-1980; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Letters on Centennial, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Pelham, Peter, 1976; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Poetry festivals, 1980-1986; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Articles on women's colleges, 1982-1987; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, clippings, class schedules, 1983-95; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Eckles Library planning, 1984; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - MVC facebook, 1986-1987; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Enrollment data, 1987-1989; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Mount Vernon Motif (Vol. 1, No. 1), 1988; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Postcards, invitations, 1988; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - MVC press, 1988 September-October; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Minutes of the Academic Affairs Committee, 1988 October 15; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Founder's Day invitation, 1988 November 14; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Faculty salary information, 1988-1989; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - The Merriweather Post (Vol. 5, Nos. 1, 3, 4, 6), 1988 September-1989 January; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Draft guidelines for awarding honorary degrees, 1989 January; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Draft model for core curriculum, 1989 January; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Awards ceremonies, 1989-1994; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - "The Best of Both Worlds" - MVC brochure, Circa early 1990s; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Pamphlets - inauguration and Alpha Chi induction, 1990-92; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Fisher, James L. - correspondence with LucyAnn Geiselman, 1991-93; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Sample invitation for the inauguration of Lucy Ann Geiselman, 1992 September; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Internship correspondence, 1993; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Reunion program and registration packet, 1993 April; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Programs for Women in Politics and Journalism Symposium and dinner, 1995 September 28; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Alpha Chi certificates (Mary R. Surrey, Sallie Rush-Wright, Frances Johnson, and Maryruth Perrone), 1996 February 22; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Student Government Association Constitution, 1997-1998; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Student Government Association memos and event planning materials, 1997-1998; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Student Government Association president Bethany Miller's records, 1997-1998; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Class of 1999 letter sent from senior class president Harjinder Gill, 1998 August 18; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - Martha's Voice newspaper, 1999-2000; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - MVC gold seal, undated; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 16)